Preliminary Inventory of the James Thomas Watkins Papers, 1927-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
James Thomas Watkins Papers
1927-1970
71040
Hoover Institution Archives
25 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 2 envelopes, 6 microfilm reels, 1 phonorecord, 1 framed painting (12.2 linear feet)
Writings, reports, memoranda, orders, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to American military administration of Okinawa immediately after World War II. Entire collection also on microfilm (36 reels).
Watkins, James T. (James Thomas), 1907-
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1971.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
American political scientist; lieutenant commander, United States Navy; political affairs officer, United States Military Government, Okinawa, 1945-1946.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, reports, memoranda, orders, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to American military administration of Okinawa immediately after World War II. Entire collection also on microfilm (36 reels).
United States. Navy.; Japan.; Military government.; Okinawa-ken (Japan); Paintings.; Phonorecords.; Ryukyu Islands.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Foreign relations.
- Bibliography (Box 1)
- Ryukyus indoctrination
- History of Okinawa
- Battle of Okinawa
- POW's and MP's
- Okinawa picture list
- Flack Valley graves photographs
- Museum and Colonel's house - photographs
- Okinawans and others - photographs
- Evacuation, resettlement, home life, orphanages, and rationing - photographs
- Personnel and parties - photographs
- Government - photographs
- Landscape, typhoon, and destruction - photographs
- Post office and special - photographs
- Architecture - photographs (Box 2)
- Agriculture, industry, and labor - photographs
- Education and the arts - photographs
- Enlargements of photographs
- Aerial photographs
- Illustrations from magazines
- Maps
- Clippings of early occupation of Okinawa, 1945-1946
- Issues of Kosei Okinawa, 1947-1948
- Clippings on Okinawa
  - 1947-1948
  - 1951-1959
  - 1960-1968
  - 1949-1951 (Box 3)
- U.S. Military Government, Okinawa, monthly reports
  - 1945 April-August
  - 1945 September-1946 February
  - 1946 March-May
  - (final report), 1945 April-1946 July
- U.S. Military Government, Okinawa, team history reports, 1945
- U.S. Military Government, Okinawa - special documents, 1946
- Okinawa - miscellaneous printed matter, student papers, and letters
- Symposium - apt quotations
- Research declassification
- U.S. Military Government, Okinawa - post office and censorship
- Indexes (Box 4)
- Chronology of U.S. Military Government, Okinawa
- Pre-occupation training of military government officers
- U.S. Military Government, Okinawa, documents, 1945-1946
- Morgan memoir on occupation of Okinawa
- U.S. Military Government, Okinawa, minutes of meetings, 1945-1946
- U.S. Military Government, Okinawa - planning phase
- U.S. 10th Army Military Government planning history
- Military Government operational plan annex
- Military government (Box 5)
  - Theory, mission and authority
  - General organization
  - Headquarters organization
  - Field organization
  - For Ryukyus other than Okinawa
  - Organization, Iji bivouac area
- U.S. Army assumption of military government, 1946 July
- Military government personnel
  - Staff assignment and station lists, 1945-1946
  - Detachment rosters and draft rosters
- Military government personnel (Box 6)
  - Enlisted personnel - guard lists and plans of the day
  - Demobilization or reassignment from Okinawa
  - Miscellany
  - General William Crist
  - Colonel Charles Murray
  - Morale
  - Fraternization, circulation and violence
- Okinawa
  - Arts, monuments and religion
  - Education
- Military government orders and directives, 1945-1946
- Hanna memoir on military government planning stage
- Okinawa
  - Land and population
  - Attitudes and psychology of population
- Hanna/Watkins manuscript on land and people of Okinawa
- Lawrence/Watkins manuscript on supply (Box 7)
- Military government documents on supply
- Supply - miscellany
- Political rehabilitation - general and miscellany
- Okinawa government - pre-war
- Okinawa Provisional Advisory Assembly, 1946
- Okinawa Advisory Council - notes on meetings with U.S. Military Government Political Affairs Officer
- Okinawa Advisory Council
- Government up to rejection of Murdock Plan
- Implementation of Caldwell Program
- Implementation of Caldwell/Mura Program
- Implementation of Caldwell Program
  - Civilian departments
  - Appointment of Chiji (Governor)
- Notes of meetings with Chiji and Cabinet
- Implementation of Caldwell Program
  - Prefectural Assembly
  - Consolidation of military government control
- Operation of Shijeka Administration
- Okinawa judiciary
- Government notes for Watkins manuscript
- Watkins manuscript on Okinawa government - first draft (Box 8)
- Okinawa
  - Economic rehabilitation
  - Evacuation, resettlement and housing
- Repatriation of Okinawans in Taiwan
- Okinawa
  - Agriculture and fisheries
  - Industry
  - Monetary economy
  - Labor (Box 9)
  - Property
- Lawrence/Watkins manuscript
  - Economic rehabilitation
  - Public health
- Watkins revision of Lawrence thesis on public health
- Okinawa - public health relief
- Lawrence/Watkins manuscript
  - Disaster relief
  - Monetary economy
- Hanna/Watkins manuscript on social rehabilitation
- Okinawa - reversionism, 1953 (Box 10)
- Hanna manuscript
  - The future of Okinawa
  - Appraisal and prospects of Okinawa
- Lessons from experience - notes and correspondence
- Okinawa
  - American relief (post-occupation)
  - Future status
- Correspondence with military government enlisted personnel, 1948-1959
- Lawrence, William Henry, Jr., "Military Government in Okinawa: Disaster Relief Administration, the Economy and Its Rehabilitation, and Supply," M.A. thesis, Columbia University, 1947
- Miscellaneous mimeographed reports, photographs and printed matter, relating to Okinawa, 1947-1969 (Box 11)
- U.S. Navy Civil Affairs Handbook for Ryukyus, 1944 (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous military government directives
- Watkins manuscript on political rehabilitation
- Nakasone, Genwa, "From Okinawa to Ryukyu" (in Japanese)
- Military government roster (Box 13)
- CinCPac-CinCPOA report on Okinawa, 1944
- Military government reports for Ryukyus, 1946 and 1948
- Photograph negatives
- War diary indexes (Box 14)
- Daily Okinawan Press Summary issues
  - 1954
  - 1951-1953 (Box 15)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 16)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 17)
- Chit book of Charles W. Ure, businessman in Shanghai, 1917
- Maps, printed matter and miscellany, relating to Japan and world politics, 1948-1978
- Reports of U.S. Foreign Service oral examination of Stanford University students, 1933-1963 (Box 18)
- Correspondence, student papers, printed matter and miscellany, relating to world government and U.S. and world politics, 1906-1972
- Press releases and printed matter, relating to the attitudes of various member nations of the United Nations toward the Korean War, 1950-1951
- Watkins Family genealogy on 4 x 6 cards (Box 19)
- Pamphlets and articles about Okinawa
- Administration of Occupied Areas, a study guide by Philip H. Taylor and Ralph J. D. Braibanti, Syracuse University Press, pamphlet, 1948
- Watkins manuscript and notes on early occupation period
- Watkins notes, war diary (Box 20)
- Okinawa public relations pamphlets
- Ryukyu Islands, a bibliography, Department of the Army pamphlet, 1967
- War diary notes (Box 21)
- Lawrence/Watkins manuscript
  - Rehabilitation, political and social
  - Supply
  - Public health
  - Okinawa: "The land and the people"
  - Disaster relief administration
  - Planning period
- War diary (Box 22)
- Correspondence, Okinawa project
- Hanna manuscript
- Watkins letters to his wife
- Trips
- Ryukyu Project expenses
- Lawrence/Watkins manuscript on monetary economy
- Watkins Okinawa papers catalogue (Box 23)
- War diary
  - Table of contents
  - Index
  - Pages 116-227
- Watkins desk calendar entries, 1945 October 20-1946 July 18
- Lt. Commander Paul H. Skuse's letters to his wife from Okinawa
- Watkins-Skuse correspondence
- Correspondence with Okinawan leaders, 1947-
- Correspondence
- Letters of recommendation (U.S. Navy)
- Correspondence with Francis W. Schruben
- Ryukyu study proposal, summer, 1953
- Writing: Okinawa oddments
- Military government chronology (Okinawa)
- Lawrence/Watkins manuscript on rehabilitation
- Correspondence, general, about Okinawa (Box 24)
- Personnel: Military government alumni
- Navy School of Military Government (class notes)
- Watkins letters from Okinawa to wife and family
- Correspondence with Mr. Iwao Yoshihama
- Reversion (Box 25)
- Correspondence with Sanford Zalburg and Arnold Fisch
- Maps and miscellaneous
- Administrative Subdivisions of Japan, 1946-1947, atlas (Box 26)
- Two maps of Okinawa
- Printed matter on the occupation of Japan, and the League of Nations
- Button given to the delegates of the World Youth Congress held in Geneva in 1936
- 1 framed oil painting, 1946, by Japanese artist O-shiro Ko-ya, depicting a scene at Shikiya with Kudaka Island in the distance, commissioned by the officers and men of the U.S. Naval Military Government (Other Art Rack)
- Microfilm reels of Okinawan Papers Deposited by Professor John T. Watkins in the Hoover Institution (Other 1-6)
  Microfilm Reel Contents List
  Downloadable PDF guide to microfilm reel contents